nv.gov 2009-08-05

# State of Nevada

                                        State of Nevada
                                    e-government Steering Committee
                                                   Policy
Control No.         Rev.                             Title                                Effective Date         Page
    3.03              B                   State Online Privacy Policy                         11/25/02           1 of 5
 1.   PURPOSE
      The State of Nevada is committed to protecting the privacy of visitors to our websites. This policy defines
      the minimum online privacy requirements for State of Nevada executive branch organizations. Any
      executive branch organization may augment this policy with information that pertaining to services offered
      on their specific website.
 2.   SCOPE
      All Nevada state executive branch organizations must adhere to the policy in this document to the extent of
      the governor’s authority. This policy applies to all state Internet sites but does not apply to state Intranet
      sites.
 3.   EFFECTIVE DATES
      The requirements of this policy are effective 90 days after sign-off by the Governor or his designee.
 4.   RESPONSIBILITIES
      Heads of all Nevada state executive branch organizations are responsible for their organization’s
      compliance with the requirements of this policy and all applicable laws of the United States and the State of
      Nevada. They are also responsible for any information captured from users who access their websites (see
      section 6. 5 of this policy.
      All Nevada state executive branch organizations must publish a link to this policy on the homepage of their
      websites. A link to this privacy policy and any additional agency-specific privacy policy is also required on
      every page of a web site that collects personal information or incorporates an e-mail or other form where
      users may submit questions or comments.
 5.   RELATED DOCUMENTS
      State of Nevada Web Style Guide Policy (http://nitoc.state.nv.us/document_index.htm)
      State of Nevada Security Policies
      State of Nevada Standardization of State Agency Web Site Home Pages
      (http://www.webmaster.state.nv.us)
      World Wide Web Consortium (WC3) Privacy Preferences Specification (http://www.w3.org/P3P/)
      Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act (http://www.ftc.gov/bcp/conline/pubs/buspubs/coppa.htm)
      Federal Trade Commission Privacy Initiatives http://www.ftc.gov/privacy/index.html
                                                                                      3.03(B)_Policy_StateOnlinePrivacy.doc

                                      State of Nevada
                                 e-government Steering Committee
                                                 Policy
Control No.      Rev.                               Title                              Effective Date         Page
    3.03           B                    State Online Privacy Policy                        11/25/02           2 of 5
 6.   POLICY
      6.1.  Personal Information:
            6.1.1. When information is Collected
            The state does not collect or retain personally identifiable information unless a person voluntarily:
                 Participates in an activity that asks for information (i.e. sending an email, participating in a
                 survey or filling in an online form). This information will only be used to respond to the
                 person’s request and to analyze trends. A message may be redirected to another government
                 agency or person who is in a better position to respond.
                 Uses an online service or transaction that requires collection of personally identifiable
                 information.
            Choosing not to participate in an activity or service that requests personal information will in no
            way effect a visitor’s ability to access any other feature of the State of Nevada website.
            If personal information is requested on the web site or volunteered by the user, state law and the
            federal Privacy Act of 1974 may protect it. However, this information is a public record once it is
            provided, and may be subject to public inspection and copying if not protected by federal or state
            law.
            6.1.2. Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act of 2001
            Nevada websites directed to children under 13, that knowingly collect information from children,
            must comply with the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act of 2001. However, visitors are
            cautioned that the state has no way of determining the age of a person volunteering personally
            identifiable information online or by email. As such, this information will be treated the same as
            information given by an adult, and may be subject to public access.
            6.1.3.         Password Information
            User names and passwords or PINs may be required to access an online service offered by a
            Nevada state executive branch organization. No representative of the state of Nevada will ever
            request a user to reveal their username, password or PIN. Under no circumstances should this
            information be shared with or disclosed to any other person. However, online systems may offer
            the built-in capability to securely assist users who have lost or forgotten their PIN or password.
            6.1.4. Correcting Personal Information
            Unless otherwise prohibited by state or federal law, rule or regulation, an individual may request
            correction of personally identifiable information. Persons concerned about information contained
            in their personal records should contact the custodian of that record, which is typically the
            organization that has collected the information
                                                                                   3.03(B)_Policy_StateOnlinePrivacy.doc

                                      State of Nevada
                                 e-government Steering Committee
                                                 Policy
Control No.       Rev.                              Title                             Effective Date        Page
   3.03            B                    State Online Privacy Policy                      11/25/02           3 of 5
            6.1.5. Public Disclosure of Information
            It is important to understand that under applicable state and federal law, various forms of
            correspondence and other communications may be subject to public disclosure.
     6.2.   Automatic Information
            6.2.1. What is Captured
            The Nevada state web portal utilizes server logs and log analysis tools to create summary statistics
            about the use of the portal. These logs collect the Internet Protocol ("IP") address of all computers
            accessing the portal, and may collect other similar information about the computer’s network.
            Summary statistics are used for various purposes such as assessing what information is of most
            interest to users, determining technical design specifications, and identifying system performance
            or problem areas.
            This data is not reported or used in any manner that would reveal personally identifiable
            information, and will not be released to any outside parties unless legally required to do so in
            connection with law enforcement investigations or other legal proceedings.
            For a complete list of information collected, contact the state Webmaster
            http://www.webmaster.state.nv.us
            6.2.2. Cookies
            The Nevada state web portal does not use cookies to collect information. However, other
            executive branch organizations are not prohibited from using cookies. If cookies are used, the
            organization must disclose the specific information regarding the use of the cookie as part of their
            privacy statement.
     6.3.   Link Disclaimer
            In order to make information available to visitors, the Nevada state web portal provides links to
            web sites of other governmental agencies and other non-government organizations. A link does
            not constitute an endorsement of the content, viewpoint, policies, products or services of that web
            site. Once you link to another web site, you are subject to the terms and conditions of that web
            site, including but not limited to its privacy policy.
     6.4.   Information Disclaimer
            Information provided on state of Nevada web sites is intended to provide immediate access to
            public information. While all attempts are made to provide accurate, current and reliable
            information we recognize the possibility of human and/or mechanical error. Therefore, the State of
            Nevada, its employees, officers, and agencies expressly deny any warranty of the accuracy;
            reliability or timeliness of any information published by this system and shall not be held liable for
            any losses caused by reliance upon the accuracy, reliability or timeliness of such information. Any
            person who relies upon such information obtained from this system does so at his or her own risk.
                                                                                 3.03(B)_Policy_StateOnlinePrivacy.doc

                                         State of Nevada
                                    e-government Steering Committee
                                                   Policy
Control No.         Rev.                              Title                             Effective Date         Page
    3.03               B                   State Online Privacy Policy                      11/25/02           4 of 5
 7.   EXCEPTIONS/OTHER ISSUES
      Any exception to this policy must be approved by organization management, the e-government Steering
      Committee and by the Nevada State CIO or his designee.
 8.   DEFINITIONS/BACKGROUND
      Base URL String - Also known as the root URL or Domain Name. The nomenclature, which identifies the
      address of a web site. The base string means the root URL. Example: www.microsoft.com is a root or base
      URL that takes a user to the first page of Microsoft’s web site.
      Cookies - A "cookie" is a small text file that a website can place on your computer's hard drive in order, for
      example, to collect information about your activities on the site or to make it possible for you to use an
      online "shopping cart" to keep track of items you wish to purchase. The cookie transmits this information
      back to the Web site's computer which, generally speaking, is the only computer that can read it. Most
      consumers do not know that "cookies" are being placed on their computers when they visit websites. If you
      want to know when this happens, or to prevent it from happening, you can set your browser to warn you
      when a website attempts to place a "cookie" on your computer.
      Executive Branch Organizations – Includes departments, divisions, agencies, units, commissions, boards
      or institutions.
      Home Page - The first page a user will encounter when visiting a web site for the first time through the
      base URL string.
      Internet – Worldwide network of networks and computers that are interconnected to communicate with
      each other through web pages, e-mail and many other services.
      Intranet – An internal, restricted private network in which access is restricted to those within a company or
      organization. Intranets provide many of the same services as the Internet including websites and e-mail,
      but access is allowed only to approve individuals within an organization.
      Links - Also known as hyper-links. Used to connect one web page to another web page via some form of
      Hyper-Text Markup Language, whether graphical or text in nature.
      Personal Information – Examples of personally identifiable information include:
                     Name
                     Address
                     E-mail address
                     Social Security number
                     Password
                     Bank account information
                     Credit/debit card information
                                                                                    3.03(B)_Policy_StateOnlinePrivacy.doc

                                        State of Nevada
                                   e-government Steering Committee
                                                   Policy
 Control No.        Rev.                              Title                           Effective Date         Page
     3.03            B                     State Online Privacy Policy                    11/25/02           5 of 5
                    Any combination of data that could be used to identify you such as your birth date, zip code,
                    ethnicity or gender.
       Portal - A website serving as a common entry point and frequent gateway to information and services.
       Web Page – Any page located on a web site
       Web Site - Public set of documents, called pages, developed using some form of Hyper-Text Markup
       Language (HTML).
       URL – Universal Resource Locator
                                                       Approved By
                    Title                                               Signature                                  Date
e-government Steering Committee Chair              Signature on File
NV IT Operations Committee Chair                   Signature on File
Governor/Governor’s Representative                 Signature on File                                             06/30/03
                                               Document History
Revision           Date                                          Change
A               02/14/01           Initial Release (Titled: Privacy Policy 5.7)
B               11/25/02           Updated and released under the e-Gov committee
                                                                                  3.03(B)_Policy_StateOnlinePrivacy.doc
